A Finding Aid to the Charles Culver Papers, 1920-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.culvchar
Archives of American Art
Charles Culver papers
1920-1997
AAA.culvchar
Archives of American Art
3.5 Linear feet
The papers of Charles Culver measure 3.5 linear feet and date from 1920-1997. This material documents his personal life and career as a watercolorist and art critic for The Detriot Free Press from the late 1930s-1967. The collection includes biographical material, correspondence, writings, business files, artwork, photographs, printed material and artifacts.
Culver, Charles B. (Charles Beach), 1908-1967
Separated Materials note
Material previously loaned in 1969 can be found on Microfilm reels D365-D367, and reel 3. Some of the material from this loan was not included in the 2004 donation and is not described in this finding aid.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives in 2004 by Sarah C. Weiss, daughter of Charles Culver.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Charles Culver measure 3.5 linear feet and date from 1920-1997. This material documents his career as a watercolorist and art critic for the Detroit Free Press. The collection includes biographical materials, correspondence, writings, business files, artwork, photographs, printed material, and artifacts. Correspondence consists of letters exchanged with family and colleagues, including E.P. Richardson, Director of the Detroit Institute of Arts.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Culver (1908-1967) was a Detroit-based watercolorist, critic, and teacher. Culver was very active in the Detroit arts community beginning in the late 1930s. He participated in many solo and group exhibitions in Detroit. His works are in museum collections, including the Detroit Institute of Arts and Whitney Museum in New York. Culver had exhibited in 5 solo exhibitions in New York. He was primarily known for his watercolor paintings of animals, a subject he studied and painted for the remainder of his life. Culver established the Watercolor Department at the Art School of Society of Arts and Crafts, later known as the College for Creative Studies, in Detroit; he taught at the school from 1960 until his death in 1967. In 1966 he became an art critic at the Detroit Free Press.
Arrangement note
The Charles Culver papers are organized into 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1926-1974 (4 Folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1920-1982, bulk 1920-1966 (1.1 Linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 5)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1928-1984 (1.1 Linear feet, Boxes 2-3, 5)
Series 4: Business Files, circa 1967-2000 (4 Folders, Box 3)
Series 5: Artwork, 1955, undated (0.5 Linear feet; Boxes 3, 5)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1923-1952 (8 Folders; Boxes 3, 5)
Series 7: Artifacts, undated (2 Folders; Box 3)
Series 8: Printed Material, circa 1930-1977 (0.4 Linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
- Biographical Material, circa 1926-1974; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1
  - Curriculum Vitae, Biographical Accounts, undated; 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diploma, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries and Memorial Exhibition Clippings, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Award of Merit from the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, bulk 1920-1966; circa 1920-1982; Series 2; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 5
  - Correspondence, 1920-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5-19)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, Folder 1.
  - Condolence Letters, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Envelopes, 1982; 1945-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 2, Folders 1-4.
- Writings, circa 1928-1984; Series 3; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 5
  - "American Show", undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Art and the Artist", undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "The Artist at Fifty", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "An Artist's Development and Precepts", undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Artists, Poverty and Proposal", undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "A Choice of Bridegrooms", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Coryllia and the Comical Boy", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Counsels for Watercolorists", undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Culver Joins Arts and Crafts", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Desire of the Dead", undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Dissenting Voice", undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "An Evening at the Art Museum", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Explanatory Narration before a 'Session with Arno Marsh'", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fictional Dialogue about Vietnam War and Pop Art, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Foreword", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Guest Editorial", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "A Happy Tale", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "I Rebuke Phillip", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Introduction to Art Study", 1964 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "It Happened in Dufferland", undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Johnny Ladyslipperseed", undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "A Late Look at the American Scene Movement and its Principle Figures", undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Lecture Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Lecture to Students, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Memoirs of Ernst Grassdauber", undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous Drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Michigan Show", undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Moments of Heroism", undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Music Tablature, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "My Village", undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Note about Death, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Notes on the Caricature", undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Notes on Imaginary Invalid Caricature", undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Notes on Importance of Being Earnest Caricature", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "Notes on the Philadelphia Story Caricatures", undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "On the 1947 Annual Exhibition for Michigan Artists" (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "One Man Show", 1967 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "One Man Show", undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "One Spring Afternoon", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Puppet Play, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "Random Suggestions for Art Students", undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "A Sarkisian Fantasy", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - "Screech Owl Indeed", undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - "A Short Introduction to Modern Art", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - "Some Suggestions for Art Students", undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "A Sorry Tale", undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - "Is the State of Michigan Culturally Disposed?", undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "Statement on 1964 Michigan Artists Exhibition" (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "The Story of Dod and the Troll Who Didn't Want To Be A Troll", undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - "The Stuff Lord Clopf Was Made Of", undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "Summer Art Scene", undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - "Talk to Art Director's Club", undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - "Trib to Ted", undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "Trombley's Garden", undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "Utopia Yet", undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - "Viewpoint", undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - "The Village", undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - "Watercolor Annual", circa 1944 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "The Way it Went", undated (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "Wicker's", undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Various Poems, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Journal, undated; 1939-1967 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Notebooks, Book of Dreams, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks, Poems and Short Prose, circa 1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, Poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks, Florence Culver, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notebooks, On the Laws of Japanese Painting, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notebooks, Misellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Writings by Others, The Art of Charles Culver, undated; 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Writings by Others, "Charles Culver" by E.P. Richardson, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Writings by Others, "Charles Culver 1908-1967", undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Writings by Others, "The Most Unforgettable Critic I Ever New" by Malcolm T. Rybalde, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Writings by Others, "For Art Treasures Worth an Estimated $40 Billion" by Sara Cauldwell Ambrosini, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Scrap Book Introductory Note, undated (Box 5, Oversize 2)
- Business Files, circa 1967-2000; Series 4; 4 Folders Box 3
  - Inventory, 1975-2000; undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Artwork Transactions, 1968-1972; undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1974; undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Guest List for Exhibitions, 1968; 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Artwork, 1955; undated; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 3, 5
  - Drawings, 1955; undated (Box 3, Folder 18-24)
  - Prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Plant Imprints, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Date Symbols on Culver Paintings, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Oversized Painting on Printed Material, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Painted Cartoons, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Volkswagen Sunshade Design, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Photographs, circa 1923-1952; Series 6; 8 Folders Boxes 3, 5
  - Photographs of Culver, 1926; undated (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, Folder 6-7.
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1923-1952 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Various Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Transparencies of Artwork, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Oversized Photographs of Culver, undated; 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    Oversized material from Box 3, Folder 28-29.
- Artifacts, undated; Series 7; 2 Folders Box 3
  - Stamp, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Stone, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Printed Material, circa 1930-1977; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  - Topic and Talk Newsletter, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 36-38)
  - Topic and Talk Layout, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Announcements, undated; 1947-1993 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, circa 1941-1977 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Catalogs, 1930; 1961-1978 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Reproductions of Artwork, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1991-1993; undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of Culver's Art Reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cartoons by Culver Including a Letter and Drawings, 1997; 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mounted Cartoons of Various Writers, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reference Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - In Memoriam Sarkis Sarkisian, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Detroit Institute of Arts, Sixty Years in Review, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)